[music]
Welcome to the lamrim mrim means steps
found This is for
me I have
lunch I don't have a fifth point and here I was having
lunch with my
wife's mother she went on in life
already and she had a boyfriend who she then
sent what
you
guys should do She sent him
away and She asked what the best
book in the world
and I had a very hard time advising her to choose
and that sa and the book that we are studying now
is the greatest book on the planet and
my teacher taught me it and three times and it
took 30 years and every time he
finished it He started again And he
taught me it in two different places and
one was in Washington and the other group was
near
and I was his
driver so I went to both of the
missions and I felt like he taught it for
30 years and It's incredible
to learn these things and this book will become the best
friend for you in your life so
keep this book close to you I
know there is a great translation of this book in
English I by the way  helped
translate so keep this
book close to you use it i
started teaching it 14 years ago and i promised to
finish it and if you i survive survive a
few more days then i will really keep my
promise and do this we will finish this
book this week after 14
years of incredible work let's
enjoy
ourselves tradition these transmission lines these
audiences that you you are
supposed to be the ones to teach
next i'm not kidding i
know you haven't come to every class for
years i don't know who did it at all
except me
but so tissues in case i
start
crying i'm begging you we will finish it
this week so please be la
please teach it to other
people my work is finished this
week it will be finished with this book and
then it will be your
responsibility you need to eat
even if you weren't here the whole time it's
okay you can listen request for
audio you can
read it it's not that
difficult okay if you were in class
but still i expect you to
teach all the books just try to
do it all  teachers of lavrim we all
try our best
we are not perfect and we just
have to try to try to teach
our students our friends I taught
this book even my mother
if you I could it means you
can
and We will finish this book This week
if everything goes
well This
book consists
of 400 letters it is about 6,000 pages in
English
and we are very close to
finishing this book When I started it
14 years ago the last book part of the
book it is about meditation about how to
break through it I thought it would be a great
strategy to first teach the end of this
book 14 years ago about shamata
in pashlyana about meditation deep
meditation and that's why I taught
meditation first because you have to
meditate step by
step It's called steps on the
path and every time I taught you
each step you had to meditate on that
so it seemed to me that it would be logical
if I first taught meditation
which is the end of the book  and then look at the whole
book and everyone
can study this book This is such a tradition
and we have come a long way
we have looked at three three
parts of this
book and there are different intentions
motivations for which people study this
book some
people study this book because
they want to stay as far away as possible from
nothing
rebirths and in them motivation I don't want to go down I don't
want to fall there after
my
death and
very and
so And what is unusual here to start This
course to
start you need to think about it so
By the way in the university of science there is no
course on how to Die in
fact everyone should know how to
Die it is one of the most important things in
this life and this book
starts the day you
die and then you go deeper and
deeper so the lowest motivation after
my death I don't want to go to the lower
worlds I want to remain a
human although everyone thinks that they will be a
human in the next
life in
my part of the world in the West we don't
believe that you live after death we don't
believe in life after death
so And those people who believe in life after
death they say I  I hope
I have as much hair as
Emelichi and not as much hair as
Geshelazhnared. That's how they
think. But to return to
this world as a human
is a very rare thing. One in a
billion if eight people in this
room return as humans, that's a very good,
good
result, that is, to return as a
human. Oh, and then you can
go back to the programs. Tim. Maybe you
can find your old kimono. Well, this is the
lowest motivation, the lowest
motivation. The second motivation is I don't want to
go back to where I have to die. I don't
want to go back to where I have to
lose my family, my mother. I don't want to end up in
such a place. I want to go to such a
place where there are no problems. And the third
motivation is I would like to become a Buddha
because a Buddha can really help an
infinite number of people on all
planets. An infinite
number. And this is a very serious thing. Become a Buddha.
I also think it's a very fun thing.
Very exciting. I really like
helping people. Today I was in a
coffee shop. I
cleaned the coffee machine
in the coffee shop, probably for
others. Imagine that you can also
help.  billions billions of
creations if you
could travel
to all the planets and I imagine that I will
sit with my
wife above the clouds and we will babysit
our granddaughter she is two
years old I hope
that we will bring her we will bring her during the
cherry blossom season
I and it is so difficult to babysit a two year
old
we bought her a school bus this
size in America all school buses are
yellow We bought her this
toy school bus you can remove the
top part here the roof of this bus
and there are tiny
children sitting and she is two years old here she places these
children in the bus one by one child at the
wheel That's how she places x and then
she herself tries to get into this
bus and it is so cute her name is [ __ ] and
she will say [ __ ]
passenger and she tries to get into this
bus with these tiny
toy children She thinks that she is this
small size and she
fits in there only her
legs her leg fits but she
tries to get in there
she is even worried  Taking care of one
two-year-old is hard for a grandpa And
when all the women leave and I'm left alone
with a child I'm like and imagine now 8
billion people and you're now taking care of 8
billion people I like it I'm
ready I'm waiting for this I'm working very hard to
become a nanny for
8 billion people and you get to the
main office of the bodhi and they give you a
planet share the planet Here is your
planet Okay I'm ready I'm going to
take care of this planet And then you
look after the whole planet I think this is
cool this is the
absolute lamrim This is this motivation the
last highest motivation motivation
lamrim I want to take care of all the
creatures on this planet I want to take
care of them so that they don't age don't
die if someone dies then I I'm
doing my job well I want
And jasmine as her group as the whole planet
and she now thinks that I want to
do even more and
here we are in this part at the end of the book We
learn that  how to take care of the whole
planet there are six known
perfections six known actions of the
bodhisattva the bodhisattva is someone who says
i want to take care of this planet you
make this decision you don't just
think about your family or your country you
think you want to take care of the whole
planet the whole world and that sounds
complicated but it's not
and one child is complicated and the
whole planet is not complicated i want to
say it's a lot of fun exciting
it's incredible helping others and the whole
world and also i really like to have
fun every day what i do i have
fun every day what i want to say and the
vibski sadvi this is the best that the best thing
you're too serious about death perish
proplanet from
death
[music]
ilann
and feels important you Superheroes don't have to
act like this feel like this is a big
party enjoy have fun this is the
best party take care of others and
you don't feel like you're getting old and you
then are so easy give me another
planet for me one is not enough we
learn to do it
and we started we continued
six actions of
the Buddha that a warrior has activities
to learn the Buddhist teacher
the first
is called
giving Dana
pereramit say this is the perfection
of giving we completed it and we are now on the second sila sila paramita this is our ethics and we left and by the way i am very proud that you all came back after yesterday i thought that some people would leave Tokyo yesterday was a very difficult day it was a very difficult lesson and i am proud that
you came back i am very happy about this
yesterday was actually a
test if people
left in the morning and did not return
nalamrim we were testing you and so we
made a difficult lesson at the beginning
unserious people they will give up and leave
and in the second lesson we are doing the real lesson the
second day and i will now show you the
Himalayan language on the screen
i am just placing seeds in
your your consciousness do not study it do not
think about it i am planting these seeds for you
for your next lives you think that
you will not learn it of course you will
learn it
i agree that  maybe in this life you wo
n't learn it but I'm planting seeds so that
you can learn it in the next one
dodo for example can learn it in one
week and ordinary people they can't
so don't
worry don't take it too
seriously this is an unusual
language I'm a linguist someone who studies
languages ​​there is an ancient
tradition that this language it seems to have fallen from the
sky and I really believe in it it is not
related
to any language very strange strange language
very strange unusual language and it is very it is
very suitable for teaching Buddhism and
good Let's
go I will speak and you don't worry don't be
upset
it's not that you still don't
go back to school I'm just planting seeds for
your next lives
you will be better off watching
next time better if I
plant now don't worry about this
So how do we practice
the perfection of ethics
morality this is actually a very complex word with a
twist in Sanskrit paramita please repeat
paramita in parotuchmpa this is in
Himalayan language please repeat
this is a very strange word  because this
perfection
this is not perfection in this
case means your ethics and that you
will not And you will never get angry You have
never stolen $5 from mom I
did this for example once that you have never
done You are
perfect but it does not it does not mean if
it means if you try it will
lead you to perfection And this
perfection what makes you perfect is
not
perfection it is not that usually what
makes you
e is perfect you become it does not
mean that your ethics are
perfect and we say pa pararamiti - This
perfection we want to become
perfection param
means in
Sanskrit yes the far side of the ocean if
you surf like moat in
los angeles and there is a big curtain and you
can
warm the
ocean and your
surfboard reaches japan it is the
far side of the
ocean and it is ect
exit eit it means to go out go out
and
enter So paramita it
means to go in VN
go into another part and this is the second
perfection and that's when I learn the
lamrim step by step  on the way I like to
use pictures
I call them pictures that represent
ideas I call it im for short
I like to show the picture
and then teach the meaning and later when
you teach your students the picture
will help you
remember it helps you
remember the picture is very useful
one picture costs 1100 and here it is this
picture
I make a decision to throw away the
trash practice an ethical way of
life and you have to decide to throw away the
trash what does that mean then there is a quote from a
sage book
called the bodhisattva vachari avatar which
is called how to live as a bodhisattva how to
become this nanny of the whole
planet and this book with instructions on
how to become this nanny of the whole planet and
it is called the hstavachar
avatar and it will be in these days it was
written 1300 years ago I will read it
to
you
so this is this very important
word
pomoysm Sam means
Sam means
mind Mind
is a
decision to give up
something for example for
example a corpse from meat
you can give up make a decision not to
eat meat I do not want to be involved in
killing animals I do not want to take
part in  this I don't want to be one of
those this is not who I want to become and that's why
this don't eat give up eating
meat my
teacher in Tibet they eat a lot of
meat They say We can't
grow vegetables we're too high in the
mountains And that's why we don't eat meat so anyway
when I lived in the monastery I
gave up meat at that time everyone ate
meat and it was a little difficult for me
and when my teacher introduced
me to other teachers He
said this Mike Tu he said eat meat
but didn't give up his negative
thoughts He always laughed at me and made fun of me
Then I'll tell you something else
interesting he he ate meat his whole life
when he was even
75 well 75 is not
old anymore He had to have
surgery He came home from the hospital
and
said I'm going to give up meat And I was
his cook I cooked for him I didn't eat
meat and every day I cooked meat for him and
he  said Don't cook me any more meat now
I had an operation Now I know
what it means and he couldn't eat meat at all
he was 30 years over me and he was joking
and at the end he said I think I'll
give up meat I'm like that and it's
called
pomla means that you decide to
refuse to
harm other people pomla means
I made
a decision that I don't
want to harm other living creatures
beings and I will try very hard I will
try not to harm other people
beings If you have you You have
a lot of pain you for example
get to the hospital and your and when you have a
doctor cuts your stomach For example then
you have this compassion for animals
and then this
dream appears You feel
compassion when you And when you
feel suffering When you have great
suffering you finally wake up And you
say I don't want to create suffering
for others I want to help them I don't want to
kill them I don't want to cut them up so that they
this decision to refuse to harm other
people is the
second perfection
sew
ethics I
tired and then there is a beautiful one
repeat shenla nepa
shila Chepa
what Chepa they
gave me this screen but it is
so
maspusnky repeat
nepachepa very very very vi
phrase DN
Kapi 600 years ago wrote the
most famous conclusion about
ethics o one of the translators
has been translating this
for five years now shavpin She
completed the comment comments
very complex
comment very very
complex
because in her own thought poem jesonkapa
says the definition of this ethics
morality definition of morality
ethics definition of the
second perfection
it
means that when you
decide to be
refused to harm other
people this is morality this is itzenka
then says that this is interesting
shidemchepa
traditionally in the ancient ancient
school the school
of abidarma
ethics it Physical and verbal and
they I
will not steal I will not kill
I will not have sex
with another partner stranger and verbal this
I will not lie I will not say
rude things I
will not do divisive language I will not
speak in vain
talk three to the body concerns and four
to the word what a complication what we do with
our mouth and to give up these seven
is an ancient ancient form of
ethics but something is
missing what you do with your mind in the
ancient form of Buddhist ethics they
focused on speaking and doing
but when tsnkapa taught this He said
that
shdenchen along with the
basis
the deepest reason for all this is what
you think you can't This remove from the
perfection of
ethics you can't be ethical is
important Well what you say is very
important that in this what you
think you can violate your
ethics but it will be no one will know
because in the mind you can think very
terrible things and then we are surprised Wow I did
n't think that I could think such
terrible things Maybe you have some thoughts
arise in your mind I want to
run this person over with a big car Oh God
then you think your mind thinks Sometimes
just terrible things but you never
say it don't do it But your mind
thinks it and No one knows about it but it
also  is an ethics in Buddhism so denchepa is
very very well
known addition jason kapa
harming
people your body with your body words and the
thoughts behind it He speaks very
clearly about it
decide to give up these
things this is
ethics say
komba
o
gompa it means to
meditate there can be G or bd and it
means to meditate if you remove the n and the
S it means to get used to something in the
Tibetan word meditation
it is done
with from meditation i.e. to get used to something i.e.
in the deep meaning we ka
meditation is to get used to doing doing
something in a certain way it is
called meditation in
ancient times also in Sanskrit it is
called
havana havana hamana
means means to be And ana means to
do And it means it leads you to
something new and this is the
meaning of the
Sanskrit word alen and it is to
make you someone new This is a very
beautiful word and in Tibetan it is here MPa is
such a word and here it is about the
perfection of
ethics And when it means that
perfection that when  you do something
means you are very good at being
careful and not harming others and that is
ethical and here he gives
the definition
now after you give the definition
you give different kinds of ethics in Buddhism there
are three kinds of
ethics in general Buddhism there are three
kinds of
ethics here by the way i see a lot of
friends from
DCI for free projects that we do and it is
so fun to talk about
Buddhism the feeling is very
nice just in this
room it is like getting out of
prison there are three kinds three and three kinds of
ethics by the way sila sila is for
ethics a sanskrit word which means
to feel a
refreshing cool breeze and this i was
walking around the city today and it
was not too hot not too cold it is like this
Cold you know
nice like a fresh apple that's like this this is the
real meaning of the word sila is to
calm your
mind freeze your bad thoughts and this is
called
sila here he says that sila
has three kinds and one the first kind is the most
basic
buddhist ethics  it's not to harm
any living being other people
mean nothing bad behavior and the first
level of Buddhist ethics
is even if you are above the sky sattva if
you can't tell
another then at least you shouldn't harm
others if you can't help then at least don't
harm the first level is not to harm
other people and then he gives he says
[music] I have
Now a financial breakthrough I
gave all my money yesterday in By the way we have
something
left there he is a
magician we have
money let's find
some money a hundred there is give
a hundred yes I have more investors no no
I'm not asking for money I really am not asking for
money I just need to go to the bank
he
says
ethics don't harm other people there are
three
flavors
like one of them
and the flavor is like three
nuances and all three
classic vows they have
this
flavor name these three
traditional types of vows
this is the
basis just don't
shout raise your hand I give money not to
those who shout but to the person who rhymes
microphone  chooses from
you so
so deci You technical people turn on please
microphone straight kiss microphone
protimuksha 66
dollars Buddhist
vows They have Three flavors like chocolate
vanilla so
strawberry And it's called biti Nytsi
praktimuksha
It means not to harm others next is the
vow batisattva beatnica
they are making four promises
which for the rest of your life to help
other people treat all
people well the first level just don't harm
other people control yourself And here is the
second
level plant the seeds
who knows how to become the nanny of the
planet the vows of
botisapa and I was talking about
this we will have a ceremony of the vows
of bodhisattva here we some friends asked to take
the vows of botisattva I usually don't
do this I
usually involve others to do it
and here is a place an hour drive from here and this is the
place where where the
first time Some of the first masters who
came from Japan and  oh
my name is this guy
so he tried to come to Japan six times
and five times his
ship was wrecked he got into a
disaster and the sixth time he got there and the
first thing he did was he went to the emperor and
asked asked to take the vows of bothis and the
ashes of this man still exist there
It's a very beautiful place I thought that me and
Stan thought together to take the vow
of podhisatva there at the same place where he
stood it will be in March so
when Sakura is in April
when the sakura flowers open the
vows of bothisato will
open We
determine there we need some special
permission from the state as soon as they
give it and as soon as we are given permission We will
do it next to this place there is a beach and
we will take the vows of
bothis there so the vows will be
super And this is a different kind it's supercharging the
vows And you would like the teacher to
introduce you to these vows and as I said
the teacher these vows are
secret but I will teach them
next year somehow and then
he says I'm going to quote for you now
atisha this is a famous
book that was written a thousand years exactly a thousand
years
ago it means light on the path structure
he
says very well known
definition of different
types of ethics first level
vows
first set of vows
is called
sotarpa in sanskrit pratimoksha pratimoksha
it
means individual freedom one by one one by
one moksha is freedom and
dollars why is it called Freedom one by
one individual freedom we have
so much money dear
it frees from mental obscurations the
path to nirvana what does one by one
prati
you told me about part of moksha it's
50 dollars And why one by one
gipson
those individuals
who who keep these
workers
and they gradually do it
but it's for 25 dollars yeah still they still got it got it
to 100
dollars if you protect these vows
then you will reach nirvana and if you don't
keep it then you will not reach
nirvana that's why they are called
individual freedom vows
individuals who will keep them They will
achieve freedom I individuals who
will not keep it will not achieve it is
clear and here is what he says
there are seven types of vows Timokshi and here is
such a contradiction there are
not seven
in fact and we have to
explain I made notes for you
and the seven that Atiso speaks about he did not
include one-day vows one-day
vows he said it is one day in total
why do we need them why do we
count them at all there are eight vows
Protimokshe we say that one-day are the
first and Tisha says Yes no and what is that
one
day then he does not include them that is
why he says seven
types What are these seven
first a person who agreed throughout
his whole life to keep seven of
these vows these are sea
vows these are the first vows these are
men and in our tradition there are also God's
life vows women these are vows since
those times when in India there were
no rights
at all I want to say
that the second is a man who keeps
in the beatnitsa the first two are the first two of the seven
that is  woman and
man third
gay mother
third vows
nun nun nun
and
monk new nun and and new monk this is
34 and fifth category
this is such intermediate such
monks and monk it was difficult to say
become was fully they needed to
keep vows longer and
show So they had such basic
vows then middle then above sixth
SMI this vows full monk and full
nun
246 vows full
monks
for for nuns
why more for nuns because
they are smarter and they can
keep more
vows nuns taught me this by the way
we had discussions on this about
now he says a very interesting thing he
says If you keep one of these
seven sets of
vows you If you
agreed to keep this for the rest of your
life and Even if it is deictic principles
then he this person to this to then this person is
ready for battle battles you
understand what happened in this room
those who
dream hundred dream to accept  vows in
where the emperor took
the vows you need to take other
vows
I brought you up to the fact that you have to
take other vows you can't
take the vows of the otchistat if you haven't
taken the basic vows it's easy right
I'm here trying to read you
the contract if you want to or don't want to take
all 154 vows they are actually
very very exciting super exciting
but you have to agree to the base 10
vows not to kill not to
steal not to mess around with other people's wives
nothing and
partners without the basic vows you
can't take the vows of
the bodhisattva say kyaava yayava means this is a
very complicated word it
means if you have the karma to come back
here during the
cherry blossom season
and take the vows and either your mind
will say Oh no I don't have a project or if your
bank account goes below
zero and that means that's good luck
If you have the luck to come and
take these vows
it's what's in your mind what's the karma in
your
mind  and there are billions of years maybe you'll
die by March maybe I'll die by
March I don't
know if you have good enough karma to
be here if you have enough
karma to get here
we don't know we hope that if you
pray to be here it will help you
create karma you understand what I'm
talking about and it will help you get karma to be
here just get here just
get
here you
understand the Chinese
master crashed five times to
get there and I don't have to say a
word
Give and in any case you understand
that if a
great master crashed his
ship five times and he did get
to the place to take the vows then
maybe then and you'll have delays on the
plane maybe you need to get there a
little bit earlier he'll
try to
stop you so plan well get
here a week before try to
go to every French restaurant
quinto that's my
plan how
we do things there So when I have to stop there
Ugh great
Stop me when the time comes it
says to get the vows
boots  sattva you have to have
vows of basic ethics those are some
types of
nkapa includes one-day vows So it has
eight This is a very interesting part when you
practice the secret scholars which we
say
call the vows of the diamond path
vajrayana when you practice the secret
teachings they say if
if you are a monk or
[music]
nun you have extra points You are easier
and you don't have to be a monk or a
nun to get the
secret vows anyone in this
room can get if you already have
vows
and of course if you still have the bases in the vows
but the highest level of success is with monks
and nuns traditionally it is so actually
anyone can get so why why
according to this
theory so the more ethics you
want to keep the more you will
keep the secret
vows if
four
or five
vows We try to translate
the vows of monks and nuns it is very
difficult because they
[music] are
tied they are like tied to some kind of
dtommy month to understand in short not  I know
what the reason is. And you need to take a
book and figure it out. So monks and
nuns are very careful. They
have learned to be
careful, for example, not to tie a
bag of spices with some kind of
string. They
have a better chance of being successful in the
secret vows. But still, each of
you
can get these vows of the
secret path. But you can't
get into the cloven path if you don't
get the vows.
But in
general, our
[music]
people have a
history. They
were dragons or on dragons. They are very
intelligent. Dragons are the
gods of the forest who took
the vows of the
podhisatov. They were able to practice
the teachings of the bodhisattva. So
you don't have to be a
human to get these vows.
So what's
better?
In general, any kind of ethics that
prepares you for the ethics of the bodhisattva
are special
practices. You don't have to take
the vows of the bodhisattva.
But those who took the vow of the bodhisattva
and  nuns or monks their
vows are much more powerful They
get an upgrade like to business class And
what first class then yes diamond
path first class is diamond path
some people say Look
heshel what are the lowest vows
protimokshi what are the lowest
vows you can say one day
vows in general
it
agree agree collect
sea
vows five of them I will not
I will not kill people I will not
steal anything valuable I will not have sex
with someone else's husband I
will not lie about seeing
emptiness these first four are basic basic
and fifth
say it again
I
agree Not to take
alcohol or chemical any
intoxicants according to ancient books
alcohol drugs
marijuana I promise that I will never
use it in my
life I was not born a Buddhist and I
was born a Christian and I was a happy
Christian I had a good experience with the
church many of my
friends when I started
studying with my lama for 30
years old rule you can't go out
use
who am I I'm
20 years old and I
bowed down to him Buddha
bless
Why did he
say that alcohol destroyed my family
destroyed my dad and I spent 20 years
watching alcohol
destroy my parents destroyed my whole whole
family and I God blessed Buddhism it's
very cool oh
if you are friends if you say that the
lowest ethics include never
drinking any alcohol then I'm with
you it's a great system because I saw as
a child what
alcohol does to good people they
were good people but they got worse worse
and
worse so don't come to Geshel and don't
say What if I want to
drink a little bottle of my
grandmother's wine for example you go to your grandmother and
she wants you to drink wine you
pour the wine for her and then
not accidentally spill your wine
I've done it many times the
whole carpet is already burgundy
so there
is a known
exception if you don't want to take
the vows then just agree to keep
10 ethical principles that permeate
all of Buddhism just tell your
mind I will just follow these 10
good deeds And that's all I
want I want this to sound
positive rather than negative I don't
like what they say don't kill Don't steal
I like protecting life protecting
other people's things
respecting other people's marriage speaking the
truth
always always
inspiring connecting people
always
speaking What
language not to
speak blah blah blah if it's better keep
quiet Don't be upset when other people
don't get things and don't be jealous when
others get something and remember and follow karma
Remember the grains and these are the ten you don't
have to take vows If you
keep these ten then you
can still become a botkisatko
this is such a cheap way to be a
bathistatva you don't have to take
vows Do you understand this as a
basis I agree not to harm other
people What do you think is the second level of
ethics the first level please at least
harm others the second help
people help
people we had  speech
at a basic institute in Peru we had a
speech there we had a breakfast with the
president of the university
he is like this can I
ask I am like this so and he and what are the different
types of ethics in Buddhism I am so glad
you asked I say first at least do not harm
other people second is help other
people third we will get to
there all types of morality
to help other people and here he is and and
here
he is I have another 10
minutes this may
include a person who has included the vow of
bethisatwa and then goes to the temple to meet for
free when I first go to the temple of my
teacher I am like
Wow this is a cool place I like the whole
picture
You that you don't know how to meet the temple I am like that
you don't know how to meet And how do you
meet the temple first you have to do That's how
you first
day he I don't know
he
you are so stupid you don't know how to go
to the temple you have to meet for free you have
we don't say well visit the temple We say
meet for free you have all your
thumbs inside inside
and you are here  so
fold your hands and you
go I'm glad to meet you I'm glad to
meet you Oh you look cool
but kitishara
just do it this is the second kind of
morality just hold your hands
properly this is also part of
ethics show your
respect to the teacher and other students this is
basic
ethics the second level of
ethics sitting in
class in classes is the second kind of
ethics because you create good
karma even if you fall asleep in
class you still
plant good seeds okay what
jetla these are also seeds and someone might
say Oh my god finally it's over
just study just do your
meditation and think
also think on the plane or on the way back
think about what you heard this is
also ethics this is Buddhist
ethics and then
later tell the students you have to teach
and
agree
with the students the basic contract between teacher
and student it's been 2 years if you are
in class and 10 minutes you just
sit and you agreed to teach
later  you are not allowed to be in
class if you do not agree to teach
further so
100 100 dollars degeshala gave his
first Buddhist
teachings Masha in the car in the car This
Volkswagen was cancel 100
dollars
see this if Mexican you know
what we are talking about this tiny Volkswagen
Yes it was
Volkswagen there are such big Volkswagens And
I have a cappuccino so
small
only one
person fits in there and my first
class it was a
postman a man who
and he came to my their door I
have a question I gave you money last time
by the way You are not supposed to
give money to postmen but if you do not
give this money then the mail does not
arrive in any
case and I am like this I gave you last
time he is like this no-no what are you
doing here this is a Buddhist temple we are
studying Buddhism here and he is like this Can I
study And I am like this and you Seriously he is like this
and he was my first student I
asked I asked the teacher if I could  I'm in
the kitchen I'll teach him he says No I don't
want the postman here Go in the car
you sit in the front and he's somewhere behind And you're
turning it's very difficult
actually when I
say You have to teach Buddhism You
have to teach
lamri I
mean also in
a cafe at the table with seven
you don't need these
here where all kinds of morality
this is how you
start you
just have dinner prepare a dish make
some kind of dinner for
thanksgiving then you say By the way
it's normal to kill a living
creature very gently very
gently
and and this This is what it means
even teach a friend in the car
This doesn't mean it will take
you 50 years to learn
you won't find 250 people in two weeks
don't think about it teach one person
on a
plane they can't go anywhere from
you
Titi buckled up oh okay then I'll tell you
now That's what it's
called the second
level of ethics
all attempts to learn something perfections
you try to help yourself or
other people is called ethics all
attempts to learn the six activities  Buddhism
is called
ethics in English or
Russian ethics is called not
killing other people
not driving your Tesla 100 km per
hour and here
I have a Chinese friend who bought a
car I don't know how he can drive well I won't
embarrass him but I think I've already
done it so the next
sentence the activity
of dhsattva concerns one of the three types of
ethics
simply Come to the
lamrim class step by step on the path
simply learn the steps in
itself is called ethics
simply in this class for 40 years
even when you were sitting there you
practiced
ethics ethics to be a good
person this is called
ethics and for another two minutes
Tim the third is the level of ethics
this is the first is
not harming other people friends this is
helping helping others and the third is
helping everyone in the world and there is a special
practice for this
called due repeat mopo shi
these are four
types How to treat your
students these are the known four ways How to
treat  your students and very
beautiful If you are in this
class if you teach a step on the path
you have an ethical
responsibility you
in if they want it of course it is very
important to talk in Buddhism we are not
allowed
to be other people your own
religion other people about You are a Jew
you want to learn about
Buddhism and as Buddhists we should not
bother other people who do
not want to hear about it you
need you need to speak
softly you want to know what I heard
Kyoto
No I do not want I write to my mother And you are
so okay and if I want to hear then
we have a responsibility to share it with
others it is a big difference where I live
We have different people who come and
knock on my
door My wife can not say No and I
can calmly say No but she has become friends with them
Come in and give them coffee and cake and they
communicate And we are not
allowed to do that on we
traditionally offer a mandala Before
class I want to
study it if we do
not if they do not offer a mandala then we
should not teach that is we were not asked
if you  flew to Kyoto and have been sitting here
all day I think you really want to
learn something even without a vandal so
traditionally we have to make a
mandala offering in our Now there will be a break and when
we come back we will talk talk about
four ways to achieve the
gifts of others love then we have a 30 minute
break and now there will be a traffic jam to the toilet Have a nice
break